hello and welcome it is March 3rd 2024
at least where I am and we're here in
active guest stream number
73.1 with Lan Kent mental gravity and I
guess all that comes along with it so
thank you for joining to you for a
presentation and then we'll have some
questions from live chat so thank you
and to you
thanks Danel my name's Lan Kent I'm here
in Melbourne it's Monday morning at 6:00
a.m. so I work at UH rmit at sort of
Tech University here where I do very
applied uh practical Research into
mental health promotion and prevention
and I think one of the ma major barriers
to progress in my field is that we don't
have a really solid scientific theory of
what constitutes mental health and
well-being and by contrast how to Define
mental ill health for the most common
conditions like anxiety and depression
so I've been working for a number of
years on a theory of mental well-being
effectively based on the foundational
and Universal experience of gravity to
try and get to the root explanation of
why positive and negative mental states
have a kind of vertical Dimension to
them so depression for example is a
painful down state anxiety is a painful
up State well joy is an up state as well
but it's Pleasant not painful and
mindfulness or calmness are Pleasant
down States so I think there's kind of
explanatory power in those distinctions
uh when we look at how gravity shapes
biology cognition and phenomenology so I
call it mental gravity but I don't mean
anything mysterious by it just a way of
modeling sort of physiological mental
and emotional states on their physical
Roots right next slide thanks
Daniel
before I start though I'd like to
acknowledge the unseed lands of the
bonang people of the Eastern colon
Nation where I'm presenting from today
and like respectfully acknowledge their
Elders past and present and next slide
again okay so today's talk we're going
to go through a few sections we're going
to start with a nice accessible anecdote
a parable we're going to talk about
Barbie uh the Barbie film and Barbie's
fall and we're going to give a quick
overview of the theory itself and then
really focus on one of the key Concepts
and controversial Concepts I think for
mental Gravity the idea of a center of
mental gravity and then relate that to
active inference sort of give a summary
of Where I Come From and then take
questions okay so let's start with a
kind of parable of mental gravity
Barbie's fall in the recent uh film
starring Australian Margo Robbie so
maybe you've seen it but even if you
haven't it's not a very uh complex
premise for the film so here we are at
the start of the film and Barbie sort of
coasting along in her usual Happy mode
so Life's good she has a strong sense of
self and the world is inherently
predictable she's happy and this is
depicted in the film as as her um
floating kind of joyously sort of light
and
carefree but uh next slide thanks Daniel
but then the whole narrative Arc of the
film revolves around her fall she starts
uniformly positive but then there's no
spoilers this is in the trailer she
experiences an identity crisis so
instead of being happy all the time she
starts feeling negative
emotions something unpredictable happens
that causes her to lose her sense of
self and on account of the loss she
experiences kind of an emotional
breakdown she says this is the lowest of
ever been emotionally and physically if
you could just click once
there and to really nail home uh the
metaphor when Barbie
Falls these are the lyrics of the really
beautiful melancholic song by Billy eyh
it's I used to float now I just fall
down I used to know but I'm not sure now
what I was made for what was I made
for so it's an existential crisis for
her that goes to the the core of her
being she's not just sad because she
lost something that can be replaced or
even someone that like dear to her she
kind of lost herself and when people get
depressed or have an identity crisis
like this we often say things like
they're going through a mental breakdown
so depression affects hundreds of
millions of people each year around the
globe it's kind of a universal
phenomenon that needs scientific
explanation but we still really have no
idea what we're talking about really I
think there's an intrinsic meaning here
in the Fallen status of depression they
can fulfill a sort of much needed
scientific
explanation you just click through to
the next slide Daniel
please okay now here's a spoiler
although you won't be surprised Barbie
ends up kind of happy again at the end
she goes from really high so it's sort
of Defying Gravity to low where she's
overwhelmed by gravity gravity to
somewhere kind of in between that's more
balanced and more grounded where she's
kind of managing gravity better so both
the song and the film end on a hopeful
note so Barbie recovers from her fall
when she rediscovers a new sense of self
and the song Now goes I think I forgot
how to be happy it's something I'm not
but something I can be it's something I
wait for something I'm made for so
mental gravity to me is not just about
falling it's also about what people are
for and what life is for so we have to
have ups and Downs they are a necessary
part of life but we all want the
positives to sort of outweigh the
negatives that's another gravity based
metaphor we want to be up more than
we're down so mental gravity is also
about how to recover from Falls or maybe
how to prevent injuries from falling
like depression so it's really a theory
of mental health and well-being of
emotional positivity of sort of human
value of what we're made for we just
click through to the next slide Daniel
thank
you okay so that's the pop psychology
version now for the proper scientific
explanation next slide
things right so far in the last sort of
12 or six or 12 months I've uh published
two papers on mental Gravity the first
of which was pretty Technical and
focused solely on depression the second
of which is shown here it's a bit less
Technical and more broadly focused on
positive and negative Mental Health
so it was in the Journal of
environmental psychology and as you can
see from the figure or hopefully you can
see in the figure it framed the theory
in terms of external environments at the
top internal environments at the bottom
and kind of intermediate socio emotional
environments in um in the middle so
we're going to take a quick tour through
this summary figure and let's kind of
start not at the top but in the middle
in the social emotional environment
where we found Barbie at a low sort of
mental and physical emotional state you
just click through a few times there
Daniel
okay and then next
slide okay so the central idea in mental
gravity is that there's a Continuum of
emotional states that range from up high
and ecstatic to fallen down and
depressed so it's not a b binary of
course verticality isn't always positive
there are sort of intermediate States so
being up can also be a negative if
you're unbalanced and say anxious about
falling and being down can feel good if
you're balanced stable and calm like in
mindfulness meditation or just regular
relaxation so these emotional states are
a combination of physical States derived
from complex interactions with the
external environment and mental States
derive from similarly complex reflective
interactions within the internal
environment so there's a kind of mapping
between physical and mental states that
mental gravity seeks to
explain so assuming this is a human
Universal throughout cultures and
evolution how does this mapping come
about what are the neural structures
that regulate it and what does it mean
to have gravity in or of the Mind next
slide thanks
Daniel okay so let's start with where it
comes from so the principle underpinning
mental gravity is called cognitive
gravitropism now gravat tropism in
plants and animals is the ability and
kind of the drive to maintain alignment
to and elevation within the
gravitational
environment so for example plants grow
vertically animals have muscular SK scal
structures to maintain verticality and
balance fish float using air sacs Birds
fly with wings Etc so these structures
and functions that regulate verticality
have positive adaptive value for
survival and evolution so maintaining
gravitational uprightness and stability
is a homeostatic function like
temperature control or pH or nutrition
whatever so if we fail to regulate our
body's interaction with gravity we die
it's as simple as that
now cognitive gravitropism is where that
positive adaptive and homeostatic value
has been
internalized and co-opted as a kind of
mental template for Value in other
domains namely socio emotional
expression or experience it's kind of
the value of the self in socio emotional
terms so this template means that we
think talk feel and act in ways that are
also gravitropic because being mentally
up and aligned is generally preferable
to being down and
misaligned so this effectively means
that the mind has a vertical Dimension
that people strive to enhance through
socio emotional structures and functions
thoughts behaviors and emotional
Expressions kind of all act in service
of a drive to optimize mental
verticality so this shows up in
languages metaphor in English happiness
is up unhappiness is down Consciousness
is up unconsciousness is down health is
up ill health is down more is up less is
down so cognitive gravitropism is what
makes these metaphors meaningful and
kind of universal because they also
appear in other cultures and language
and languages and even in preverbal
infants so mental gravity predates
language in development at least and
next slide thanks
Daniel which brings us to where uh
gravitropism comes from so we're at the
top we're in the external environment so
it's interactions with the external
physical environment during childhood
development so gravity has been a
constant through human evolution it
hasn't
changed but its effects are not
constantly felt throughout early
development so embryos begin life
suspended in amn iotic fluid sort of
floating in a state of neutral
buoyancy but this doesn't last long as
fetuses grow during pregnancy gravity
becomes more and more Salient as their
mass increases their buoyancy um becomes
negative I think until finally the
gravity support of their mother's womb
is kind of taken away when they're when
they're born into a gravity Laden world
so babies and children then have to
learn to control their body underg
gravity so mastering all kinds of
postures and
movements so children strive through
effort to approximate that embryonic
foundational effortless experience of
buoyancy by maintaining increasingly
complex states of verticality and
balance as effortlessly as possible so
this learning involves a lot of falling
obviously which is the opposite of
buoyancy so there are complex
neuroanatomical structures that help
children adapt and adopt that sort of
complex balance function so the
vestibular system which includes the
posterior insular cortex regulates
verticality through graviception to
maintain bodily balance control gate and
all the other physiological functions
required to optimize bodily states with
respect to
gravity and so up to this point it seems
like we're just talking about physical
States right well actually no not even
at this foundational level because grav
acception the sensing of gravity the
perception of gravity also impacts
higher order cognitive processes related
to selfhood so the feeling that we are
our bodies that embodied is deeply
rooted in the fact that our body has a
center of gravity so the egocentric
perspective from which we view the world
is anchored in the feeling that we can
exert control over a distributed body
weight
but the mental doesn't actually stop
there so it goes to the next level so
next slide thanks
Daniel so by interacting with physical
gravity children also learn to simulate
those interactions without feedback from
the external environment so you can just
imagine yourself moving and the effects
of gravity on your
body now whereas physical gravity with
feedback is mediated by the post ior
insular cortex in the vestibular system
simulated physical gravity is mediated
by the anterior insular cortex and as
you may know the anterior insul is part
of the salience network that regulates
attention inter reception effective
responses to homeostatic
signals and most importantly for mental
gravity socioemotional expression so
this is how physical gravity states have
been co-opted or mental gravity so the
anterior insular cortex takes gravity
that begins as an external physical and
embodied um physics and applies it then
to the internal inter receptive
effective environment you can just click
once there Daniel
please so hopefully you can see a little
pink ring around physical state is that
where you're up
to
yep so that's where the physical states
in the socio emotional environment
derived from That's How
gravitropism has been copied from the
external world and applied internally as
a template for social emotional meaning
and just click once more thanks Daniel
or actually twice
more but what about the mental States um
derived from the internal environment
where do they come from so are they just
inter receptive like the anterior insula
well no that's just the present state of
the physical body so Barbie didn't have
a fever or have an upset stomach she had
an emotional reaction to an event that
deviated from her long-term kind of
entrenched prize expectations and World
model so the internal mental states must
reflect long-term states of the self as
derived from autobiographical memory and
this is where the rubber really hits the
road uh for mental gravity
next slide thanks Daniel you got to
click a couple of
times so here we are we're looking at
the sort of top to bottom in the middle
of the of the figure So Physical gravity
states are the present
state of the embodied self as regulated
by the insular cortex so both posterior
and anterior mental States however are
not restricted to the present and so are
not physically embodied so their source
is from the past in the form of
autobiographical or narrative sense of
self so it's not the what and where kind
of embodied self but the more diffuse
who sense of self that is disembodied in
a personal story or a narrative so in
the diagram that's what's represented
down the bottom in the internal
environment so that's life's ups and
downs and thanks to cognitive
gravitropism these mental states have
adopted the structure of physical States
just as it feels good to be physically
up and stable in one's body because it
has a positive adaptive value it also
feels mentally good to have a higher and
more stable sense of self so self-esteem
self-worth
self-regard so these the bases of mental
health and well-being because they are
higher more pleasant value States than
their opposites so health and happiness
are up ill health and unhappiness are
down have we just click uh once there
please
Daniel so when Barbie's life story dips
unexpectedly she feels low in terms of
selfworth on a scale of verticality
value as I call it and then click again
please and so she experiences a down
state of having fallen and once
more and she simultaneously feels low
mentally and
physically now to this point none of
this is counter inuitive or
controversial I don't think some of you
may be thinking at this point so what
this adds nothing explanatory because it
doesn't give us sort of a causal
mechanism it just describes a process
Without Really nailing down how it
happens well this is where it gets
possibly controversial but definitely
counterintuitive this next bit is the
stretch point so next slide please
Daniel so my radical proposal is that
the narrative or remembered sense of
self also has a center of gravity just
like the physically embodied present
sense of self so think of it like this
we all agree that the mind has a
structure so memories
accumulate associate by learning and
self-organize into a complex network of
nodes and
connections well if we take that
structure literally and not just
metaphorically if we assume bya
cognitive gravitropism that the
structure has a vertical Dimension so
some nodes are higher in the network
than others or hierarchy then we can
also assume that this structure can
collapse so if the network undergoes
sort of Rapid or radical reorganization
such as when Barbie encounters the shock
of negative feelings those high parts of
the memory Network structure May no
longer be supported by the lower parts
so the center of gravity the point at
which gravity exerts vertical force on
the
network will therefore fall and the
person will experience a lower mental
state than they had enjoyed
previously actually don't are we on the
soci emotional state is that what the
heading is there
cool so I realize that that may sound
utterly ridiculous on first hearing it's
not something we're accustomed to think
thinking about so we like abstract
conceptualizations of the mind not
concrete ones like this we like to
imagine the mind is kind of a diffuse
ethereal and immaterial object that has
no discernable physical properties
especially rudimentary physical
properties uh like Mass but I think the
principle of cognitive gravitropism sort
of forces us to change our change our
conception of what constitutes the mind
so it's obviously non-physical
immaterial and purely mental object but
that doesn't preclude the possibility
that it has analogous physical
properties in fact if embodied cognition
is true then it makes sense to assume
that the disembodied mental World
retains some properties that mirror the
physical
world all right next slide thanks
Daniel okay so let's look at the concept
of the center of mental gravity in a bit
more detail because it all kind of
hinges on this
point okay next
slide
thanks so this isn't a new idea and it's
actually not mine so philosopher Dan
Dennett in 1992 so he coined the term
the self as a center of narrative
gravity so he used this as a metaphor
but it was a serious metaphor to convey
the idea that the self is not a mental
object you can place kind of within a a
memory content but rather a point around
which everything else
revolves and by everything else he meant
autobiographical memories okay here's
the analogy so the body center of
gravity is not a fixed location it
depends on the body's posture and
movement well the same goes for the
sense of self it's not fixed in one
place on one concept it's an abstraction
it's a point in mental space and like
the body center of gravity it can move
depending on how the narrative is
changing and what new memories are
accumulating around that Central
Point okay that's one way to conceive of
the center of mental gravity in
conceptual terms or philosophical terms
another is in neurobiological terms and
the default mode Network just a click
once please
Daniel so more recently Christopher
Davey and Ben Harrison from the
University of Melbourne here in my
hometown so talked about the default
mode Network as the brains Center of
gravity so leaning on denn's idea of
narrative gravity they observe that the
default mode Network represents that
narrative or even integrated sense of
self so it generates a high order
abstract representation of selfhood
derived from autobiographical
memory so it integrates memory to
abstract out the central protagonist the
self and they also showed on a
neurological level how the default mode
Network performs this integration
by kind of placing itself at the center
of the global connectome Network and
just click once there thanks
Daniel so in another paper these same
authors put forward the idea that the
self exists along a dimension from
experiential to narrative polls so the
experiential self is basically
homeostatic States as regulated by the
salience network and the narrative self
is autobiographical States
regulated by the default mode so this
connection between those two is very
important for mental gravity in
associating those gravity simulations
performed by the anterior insula to the
narrative processes performed by the
dmn and next slide thanks
Daniel so this idea of centrality of the
dmn is backed up by many neuroscientific
studies of structural and functional
connectivity
so along with the cognitive control
Network or Central executive Network as
I call it nodes of the dmn are the most
globally connected regions of Cortex so
this places the dmn at the top of
cortical organization because the nodes
are most dissociated from lower level
primary sensory motor cortex and just to
click through there Daniel things so in
terms of topological organization this
means that the dmn is positioned at an
extreme of the cical hierarchy because
it processes self-related information
that is s detached or unrelated to
immediate sensory input it processes
long-term trends in memory and
narrative and one more click please
Daniel so as argued by carart Harrison
friston this placement of the dmn at the
top and center of the cortical hierarchy
means it's functionally Central for free
energy minimization and the
phenomenology of selfhood the
ego and next slide thanks
Danel so if the mind has structure
including contents that are arranged
vertically and prone to Falling then it
makes sense to also speculate that
memory has a kind of mental Mass upon
which gravity is exerted just one click
through please
Daniel and so that's where the anterior
insular cortex comes back into the
picture so it is a key node of the
experiential self because it sits ATP
the hierarchy of neural processes that
extend from the peripheral nervous
system to the brain stem and subcortical
regions that making up the brain's
Central autonomic
network but remember it also regulates
the simulation of gravity and so the
assumption is that simulated
graviception acts upon an imaginary
mental
Mass so Barbie kind of imagines her
mental narrative self falling even
though her body is not falling but then
because she has imagined it kind of
self-fulfilling prophecy maybe it's
self- evidencing I'm not sure her body
then follows suit and she feels
physically low so gravity is part of how
the present self interprets information
derived from the narrative self in terms
of gravitational homeostasis so remember
that embryos begin life floating in
amniotic fluid so that is a foundational
state of cooh homeostasis inside the M
mother's womb that's referencing Anna
chuka's work with Nick Wilkinson and
like temperature and pH and all other
homeostatic set points or attractors
deviations from gravitational
homeostasis yield negative affect so
feeling heavy feels bad feeling light
feels good so Begins the film floating
through Barbie land but then when she
encounters negative affect for the first
time she feels heavy and low physically
and
emotionally not that she had a childhood
at all but her narrative has deviated
from that embryonic foundational sense
of self so her state of gravitational
homeostasis is way outside her prior
distribution but it is not physical
gravity that caused her to lie down it
was mental
gravity and and next slide thanks
Daniel okay so that brings us to the
second last section so the relation to
active inference so that idea of
violated gravity PRI brings us to um the
free energy principle and active
inference so I'm not an expert at all
but I think there are some connections
that we that can be made between mental
gravity and themes within the active
inference field and next slide
thanks so the tenets of mental gravity
map nicely onto the basic puristic of
active inference so just one click there
please Daniel so external States would
map onto the bodily interactions with
the external gravitational environment
centered on the vestibular system and
posterior insular cortex and just one
click
through sensory States would map onto
the activity of the anterior insular
cortex the experiential and embodied
self which combines homeostasis and and
affect with simulated
graviception and next
click thank you so internal States would
map onto the default mode activity so
the inner workings of the mental
narrative self with its Center of mental
gravity and one more
click and active States would be the
combination of sensory and internal
States via social emotional expression
in thought language and behavior so
they're the descriptive similarities but
I think there are deeper conceptual
parallels as well relating to that
radical idea of a center Center of
mental
gravity and next slide thanks
Daniel yes yeah thank you so this study
by Kang at L exemplifies what I mean in
free energy terms about the centrality
of the dmn so they looked at energy
Landscapes of brain States using um
estimating using pair pairwise maximum
entropy of resting state fmri so they
identified multiple local Minima some of
which mediate multi-step transitions
towards the global minimum so what is
the global minimum so it says here
co-activation of the prefrontal cortex
and default mode network is captured as
the global
minimum so as well as being Central the
co-activation of the internally oriented
dmn and externally oriented Central
executive Network
kind of represents the Baseline of the
brain's energy landscape so in healthy
or unpleasant States healthy or Pleasant
States the dmn and Central executive
Network act together to maintain a sort
of stable mental
Baseline but what happens when that
Baseline becomes unstable or moves away
from a homeostatic set point in
pathological or painful
States next slide thanks
Daniel so a recent study by friston and
colleagues demonstrated that in
depression when I would argue the
Baseline kind of drops there is a shift
away from the central executive Network
and Def towards the default mode and
salience networks so in conjunction with
sensory networks and the C
cerebellum so the self has become even
more Central in an unbalanced way that
people experience kind of as a fall away
from that external world and into
themselves so rather than feeling
connected to the World by a sort of
permeable boundary it is as though their
sense of self has become their entire
world so their past becomes all that
there is the future out there recedes
away from a never ending past in here
that they cycle through in
rumination so next slide thanks
Daniel so that's what's depicted here in
this figure in my earlier paper on
mental gravity with reference to the
Continuum of mental gravity States so up
the top of the figure on the right the
self-world boundary is kind of where it
should be in positive up or down States
like joy and relaxation so the salience
network is paying at least some
attention to the world and so there or
directing attention to the world and so
there is a clear distinction between
self and
non-self in depression at the bottom
however when people feel down and low on
account of a fallen sense of self
there's a sense in which the increased
centrality of the dmn narrative self
enlarges kind of the weight felt at
their Center of mental
gravity which then pulls the salience
network which is kind of at the boundary
down and within that self-world boundary
so anxiety is included in that diagram
in the middle but I'm skipping over that
at the
moment so now gravity in physics is
equivalent to space-time curvature so
Mass distorts space and time so I make
the case in this paper that this literal
depression of the mental self is akin to
space time
curvature across all levels of
phenomenological cognitive and neural
Dynamics next slide thanks
Daniel now this is where for me it gets
very interesting for active inference
and the free energy principle because
the physics of SpaceTime the general
theory of relativity can be considered
part of the gauge Theory framework as
argued by sen Gupta edal in this paper
from a few years back so mental gravity
if considered a form of curvature of
neural cognitive and phenomenological
SpaceTime could also be integrated
within this gauge Theory uh neuronal
gauge Theory framework just one click
through please
Daniel
so consider this quote from their paper
so crucially the cognitive homologue of
precision waiting in attenion is ATT
tension which suggests suggests gauge uh
fields are intimately related to
exogenous attention in other words
attention is a force that manifests from
the curvature of information geometry in
exactly the same way that gravity is
Manifest when the SpaceTime Continuum is
curved by Massive
bodies so for me there's a clear
connection between mental gravity as a
principle that connects external and
internal environments via social
emotional expression and mathematical
Frameworks underpinning active inference
that are already kind of flirting with
the analogy between space-time curvature
in physical gravity and psychological
Properties or
processes and next slide thanks
Danel so as an aside before I I finish
up I also think there is a way to
implement space-time curvature of
general relativity in the brain in a way
that is consistent with the tenants of
mental gravity and SpaceTime curvature
of cognitive and phenomenological Fields
especially for depression so this is a
work in progress with Dennis lean we
don't agree on everything and he
certainly doesn't agree um that mental
gravity is implicated here but he he's
the author of a relativistic model of
the SpaceTime connect time so there's
more to come on this we'll keep
working and that's kind of it that's a
lightning tour of mental gravity so my
theory of kind of what we are made for
so the main objective is to provide a
model of mental well-being of being up
and stable this is what I believe we are
made forth um according to gravitropism
and gravitational homeostasis so you
call it what you like human flourishing
happiness meaning in life however you
want to phrase it so that's it thanks
Daniel
all right thank you and thank you for to
you and the audience for bearing with
some slide fun as we discovered the
minutes before beginning but well done
okay well people watching live can add
any questions but uh while they are
adding any questions in the chat just
how did you get to this project how did
you get to active inference what just
kind of LED you to being here
now so originally the connection
happened sort of in my undergrad I was
studying psych and physics at the same
time when we were doing um sort of black
hole physics in astronomy and
astrophysics and we were talking about
depressions in SpaceTime and then an
hour later we were talking about you
know depressions in
Psychopathology and I think it was
really a linguistic thing that got me
first I'm oh okay we're talking about
very similar things here that people
seem to feel down and dark and slow and
heavy and we've just been modeling that
mathematically in physics I wonder if
there's a way to use that maths to model
something about about brain structure or
function and then during my PhD I
connected with yakob hovi here in uh
Melbourne who's doing self- evidencing
and I think studied under Carl back in
the day and so he introduced me to
active inference and predictive
processing we published a on that as
part of my PhD and so I started thinking
about okay there's something about prior
and and you know Human Experience of
gravity that is
probably expressed somehow in mental
States in mental well-being and that's
kind of what draw me drew me to
it all right cool well I look forward to
any questions in the chat but I just
kind of wanted to reiterate what I
thought was one of the core points POS
Ure is basic to moving animals and to
mammals and you pointed out that that
gravitational homeostasis is like pH or
nutrition or sleep it's a
fundamental moving set point situation
if you want to get over a small fence
you might want to briefly have the
distribution of your physical center of
gravity move up you might like plan out
different routes just like you might
plan for your or um implicitly or
explicitly like your glucose levels to
fluctuate and so that kind of like
skillful
competency definitely connects to the
fields and leaven work in the competency
and generalized State spaces so then
that kind of navigation plus
gravitational homeostasis becomes
co-opted analogously to how the
linguistic does like evidenced by your
most recent answer but the gravitational
homeostasis
becomes
co-opted as part of navigational which
is as a cognitive or narrative degrees
of freedom in generalized State spaces
and there's just so many ways to go and
it was awesome how you laid it all out
so again thank you for presenting thank
you where do we go from the center of
gravity basian mechanics what kinds of
older data sets
theories do you think are like worth
revisiting or what kinds of approaches
does it open
up
um I've worked with uh Paul Badcock who
works on the hierarchically mechanistic
mind as well he's in Melbourne here so
he's worked with Carl and others to
Define sort of evolutionary and
developmental nested time scales um
inference and I think that you that kind
of nesting of present experience within
developmental experience within I don't
know cultural and evolutionary
experience I think is's a way to um way
to approach it so gorg norof who was
maybe going to join us here today but
hasn't been able to make it so he would
talk about nested time scales in even a
a theory of Consciousness that that
nestedness is the necessary part of
necessary part of experience and
deviations from nestedness lead to pain
so those homeostatic set points are
nested um so I think there's work to be
done there in the experience of time is
really where it started for me the
experience of time dilation in
depression to me is analogous to
gravitational time dilation so masses
curve SpaceTime so that time slows down
there's very good empirical evidence
that in depression people experience a
slowing of their conscious experience so
not it's not like their internal clock
is running slowly it's not like they Mis
judge times all the time I think there
are really fine technical ways to elicit
changes or distortions in their time
perception but their subjective flow of
conscious experience definitely slows
down so in Mania the opposite of
depression
that experience of time speeds up in
anxiety another Upstate it's also sped
up kind of
chaotically so I think there are ways
to I think pull out okay what's your
experience of time and then how do we
sort of recover that how do we renest
that
through whether it's postural or I think
maybe better to have you know
mindfulness medit meditation that uses
simulated gravity so asking people to
imagine themselves floating so I do a
lot of yoga and part of my practice is
Imagining the body lights that's all
postural and it's trying to imagine all
the
movements a bit like ta Chi that there's
there's no weight you're just moving
freely and so that seems to me to
improve mood I think because that center
of gravity the physiological center of
gravity has then fed back on the
emotional state on the The Narrative
sense of self because they're connected
the anterior insula doing that
simulation it's connected to the default
mode and there's some feedback there so
I think time and sort of perceived
imagined body weight are two ways to
sort of attack the
problem all right awesome all go to a
question in live chat upcycle Club
writes how does the concept of mental
gravity influence the perception of time
and space in astronauts versus normal
folk okay that's pretty complex so
because they go from a state of you know
regular gravity to micro gravity in
space and then back again so Studies
have been done showing that
there's um sort of visceral changes
visceral and physiological changes in
space that lead to
um
it's not again it's not a change in
perception of time but there's or space
so the perceptual field remains
pretty um unchanged but when people come
back to earth and they they sort of re
acclimatizing to gravity there is a
tendency to experience anxiety and
depression now that could be related to
the fact that they've just left the
space station and they're back on Earth
and they're feeling a bit you know bit
let down by it but there's there's
ongoing work happening that
um I think they've just done actually
some psychophysical experiments with the
perception of time and they're not
noticing I don't think
anything um major other than sort of the
sensory motor stuff so people are having
to like when babies are born they have
to recalibrate how they move for Gravity
there's a an adjustment period where
people have to um reac climatize and re
sort of retrain the sensory motor
Network to let go of the gravity
expectations I'm not actually hugely
conversent in that that's somewhere that
I need to learn more about because the
work that's been
done yeah it's it's it's formative but
yeah we're getting
there cool one thing that that mention
of the microgravity and and the call
back to the developmental part made me
think of and you referenced and C
unica's work then is is like in the
Single Cell water environment there's a
neutral buoyancy so that means that all
so all
subsequent gravitational homeostasis can
be attributed to self and movement
whereas um nutritional
homeostasis has a weaning off of and
never a complete weaning off of but
gravitational homeostasis really remain
me but also from the very beginning as
something
that um it can be inferred reliably over
evolutionary time scales that it is
under that mammal's agency yeah exactly
yeah it's a universal constant and we're
now pushing the boundaries of it by
getting ourselves into microgravity
where you know no animal other than I
suppose fish you know get neutral
buoyancy and I think there's an argument
that Nick and Anna make in their paper
on sort of buoyancy in utero that what
we're trying to do all the time is
approximate neutral buoyancy with
posture and movement that it's the
feeling of load that is a deviation from
that ideal State that's the the
prediction area era that we're trying to
minimize is the feeling of load and
there's another uh there's a person in
America who's a
gastroenterologist who's working on
gravity in the gut and linking that to
mental health conditions like anxiety
and depression through irritable bow
syndrome and his idea is that sort of a
failure of the gravity support
mechanisms in the gut leads to you know
changes in the gut
microbiome that we then interpret as you
know a change in G forces it's like the
gut is uh a gForce Accel accelerometer a
bit like your vestibular system senses
changes in the head the gut also has you
know propri acceptive visceral um
sensors for acceleration and that's why
we say we when we're nervous or anxious
we've got butterflies in the stomach
it's like the the gut has become light
and that's from top down
predictions a bit like Barbie saying I'm
I've had this fall and now I'm lying
down your expectation when you're
nervous is that you're under threat and
that there's some change in the
gravity um acceleration that you're
feeling in your gut so here and I in
conversation so talking about how the
gut brain connection could be you know
another way of exploring mental gravity
as you know not just brain and nervous
system um your central nervous system
but also your peripheral nervous system
and and visceral feedback and and that
works for predictive processing because
Inter reception is very top down um
dependent wow makes me think of yes
butterflies in the stomach and also
heart or stomach sank like a stone sank
Like a Rock which is to say like the
prior experience no resistance under the
constraints of normal freef falling
things it went down at this acceleration
and uh to ask about that linguistic
angle like are there any metaphors that
aren't consistent it seems like in
day-to-day conversation it would almost
be taken as a strange metaphor if
something were inserted kind of like
Kandinsky who asserted that warmer
colors were associated with light and
with higher notes of music and like
cooler slower darker and lower notes and
it was like well if that when violated
surprises people then that speaks to the
nature of that associative prior but I
mean are there any linguistic examples
or anything that not that I've come
across no because I I assume that it's
preverbal that children have um you know
natural associations between higher
space and you know certain
characteristics so more we have a
metaphor that more is up so we're saying
you know greater value higher value is
more things and babies will attend to
higher space when there are fewer things
than um when there are lower so that
violates their expectation they expect
more detail in higher space so it's yeah
I think it's Universal across in English
across languages and because it predates
language so I'd be very surprised if
there was a contradictory metaphor the
one that there are behavioral um
Expressions that are kind of
contradictory so I think of when
people say win uh a tournament so
they've exerted all their energy and
they win often they'll fall down they'll
collapse in sort of joy and so that's
kind of a behavioral
contradiction so I think taking it it
too simplistically is going to be a
problem because you know counter
examples will be easily found but I
think there are ways to frame that in
terms of mental gravity it's not just
it's a very complex interaction with the
gravitational environment so lying down
feels good sometimes so what they're
expressing or what they're experiencing
emotionally at that point is kind of
being overwhelmed by the volume of
emotion that they're feeling so it's
still an expression of something
gravitational it's just kind of inverted
so I don't want to be too simplistic
about it and say up is always good
balance is always good because in play
in Risk moderate risk taking falling is
good so we've got to be very nuanced
about the language that we use yeah
great all right question from Dean
tickles the response to being embedded
in a gravitational influence setting
seems to be quite distinct from being
embodied so what does a buoyant mindset
look like always good question
mark yeah I think it always feels good
but whether that's always so
homeostatically feels good whether
allostatic that is is always good I'm
not sure so if alisasas is about the
prediction and
anticipation I always think of sort of
MDMA at this point so there's a tradeoff
so people will take MDMA to get high and
to have a super ecstatic super
buoyant it's almost like gravity doesn't
exist they can dance for hours but then
two days later they're going to hit the
wall and have a huge come down so I
think it feels good in the moment
because that's the anterior insula
homeostatically saying this is great
this is cool but then the dmn is maybe
going to anticipate and
say this isn't going to be great for our
narrative there's going to be a longer
term uh cost to this experience as well
so yeah it might feel good in the
present but that doesn't mean it's going
to feel good in the long
term then we've got Anna joining us have
we yes
yeah did that answer the question though
did that get to the the heart of that
person's question I I hope so yeah cool
and are you
here hey hi Anna how you
going I'm okay how are
you well thank it's very late here I
don't know what time is there but it's
like it's Sunday
evening we're
here we're in a three sector
conversation which is uh you know
equidistant but also some of the most
fun to coordinate as we know yeah yeah
yeah yeah um do you wan to like say
anything or ask anything Anna or or we
can continue talking or reading other
questions no no no I don't I I don't
have questions for now so good okay cool
yeah another thought or area was you
talked about up and down
but under a closed Planet structural
model up is out and down is in it is
gravity so it doesn't it's that we can
have a meter stick coming perpendicular
or normal and talk about up down in a
reference point but isn't that the whole
question about whether you're up is my
up and whether your toilet flushes the
same way and all these like questions
like that is your left my right all
these things yeah so I think for like
neurologically the representation of out
is into the external environment so
that's the central executive Network
that's the main mediator there and so
we're connecting with the external world
that way our default mode is our
internal world but we also have to
imagine what other people have inside
their internal world so there's you know
what's someone else's narrative so that
has to then connect with other people's
up and down so I think being able to
then so children start very egocentric
and very you know they're not mind
readers at that point so then to be able
to not only disembody their own sense of
gravity or their own Center of narrative
gravity to then apply that to other
people involves another turn another
okay that other person is out there and
they have an internal
World um as well how do I engage with
that and that takes then behavioral
coordination in the external world so
behavioral control empathy and
self-control or compassion and
self-control go very much together so in
that sort of relative space of multiple
Minds multiple centers I'm just centered
in my own but I need to connect with
others I need to be able to regulate my
behavior if
I'm manic and self-interested and every
everyone's up is my up then that's
dysfunctional I think or socially and
emotionally not going to connect with
people well that's why we kind of term
it I don't like saying pathological but
that's why we term it as socially
dysfunctional and unsustainable in a way
it's not they're not embedding
themselves in that social environment in
a way that acknowledges that other
people have different orientations that
their up might be my
down just to kind of like echo part of
that um when there are Polar Opposites
it's a polarized antipodal situation um
one's up as the other one's down but
even someone standing relatively next to
you has a partially diverging
perspective except when there's the
construction of the flat playing field
like an ice rank or something that's
been then secondarily engineered to be
even flatter than the local curvature
like a linear accelerator for particles
is extra flat which allows extra
measurement accuracy coordination but
then as it goes further and further out
it becomes like a larger and larger
project to maintain all of that yeah
[Music]
Anna yeah so I since I uh I read your
paper L is um I said next next time I'm
going to see you I'm going to nag you
with a question okay about this because
um I wonder how much of this like um
narrative between you know up is light
and good and down is bad so low it's
coming from this like
inherited um you know inherited um
ontology where you know
the light and God is somewhere in the
you know the sky and uh the devil and
the hell is in the Earth right is down
yeah so basically we want to escape the
hell and the the the death because we
are all going to die and you know Earth
to Earth ashes to ashes you know yeah we
want to just like go up and uh and
that's that's good in that sense right
because we well nobody wants to die and
I think
I I love that because um you know um p
deola and all this Renaissance people um
when they were fighting against uh the
church was like stating that the Earth
was in the middle of the universe and
actually everything was revolving around
Earth and they were refusing the idea
that you know um actually is the sun is
not the Earth and then they were saying
well if the hell is in the middle of the
Earth and everything revolves the around
the earth so everything revolves around
the hell the universe that kind of like
ring the bell ding ding ding you know
the heads of those people like higher up
in this like I think from now moment on
I kind of like realize that okay so
maybe there is something about the sun
which is like you know the Heat and the
but my question to you is like how much
of this do you think is kind of like
related because in in in a sense like
the food is coming from the D
I mean the food is coming from the earth
right so everything that actually allows
us to survive it's not so it's so don't
you think that somehow this like we have
like some side effect of some very old
ontology that we inherited where you
know God is in the sky and it's good and
it's Eternal and death is here and it's
bad right with the Earth but that's
question because I said it's like if we
don't have the carrot and the carrot is
not coming from the sky it's coming from
underneath that right so how how you
reconcile
that so I think like being absolutist
about it is a problem and saying that up
is always good no matter what down is
always bad no matter what I think even
in our Behavior or even in like a mature
approach to
life a balance of up and down is
required you don't want to be happy all
the time there's no adaptive value in
that you have to go through trials and
tribulations so a kind of
childlike I want to grow up and I just
want to go to the stars and you know be
Superlight and be sort of divine I think
is kind of you know
counter counterproductive in a way and I
think like we have words of being
grounded and of being mindful that are
very down oriented so I think there is a
value in things that are here that are
stable that are um connected that are in
Balance like a lot of environmentalism
is about Humanity in balance with nature
so that's possibly even more
ontologically prior than monotheism and
the idea that you know everything up is
good yeah I I agree with you but you
know it's just like when um when I'm
very tired right like for instance right
now just like lying down is actually
goodly want to stop and lay down I don't
want to go up right so so it's it's a as
you said it's like it's balance yeah and
we need to be careful not to smuggle in
a sneak in without realizing some like
from the kind of like you know dualist
ontologies like we have God and the
things good in the sky and bad things
are here which is yeah yeah yeah that's
just like a coping mechanism is I don't
think that's that holds because we
actually need to lay down
yeah exactly actually half of our life
is like we're lying down because you
know we need to sleep yeah so I think
there's a kind of a
way out of that sort of paradox and like
in monotheistic religions they're
talking about the afterlife in a sense
like that's like if you had a bird's eye
view of your entire life it is if you'd
never gotten up if you'd never been
vertical you wouldn't necessarily be you
know classified as having lived so it's
a necessary condition to get up but it's
not sufficient it's not doesn't suffice
the whole you know all the contents of
that life so you can say well if the
religious people want to talk about that
then that's an afterlife reflection it's
not a lived embodied way to be that is
more about balance and the complex like
we were saying the complex nuanced you
know if I fall down that can it's like
you can cry from laughter and tears you
can fall down from depression and
ecstatic Joy so it's about understanding
those those complexities that makes it
real world and not mythical so yeah in
the paper or I can't remember which one
I said this is what mental gravity is
not it's not about the fall of Man it's
not about you know some mythical sense
it's not about quantum gravity it's just
about def trying to Define and model all
our complex social emotional states
using gravity as that prior experience
the
template
yeah I'll ask a question from the live
chat um upcycle Club writes in terms of
embodied information processing the
brain processes information at different
granularities how does this impact our
conscious experience of mental
gravity well I look at uh sort of spatio
temporal granularity there so spao
temporal scale so I think a lot about
time and the nestedness of temporal
scales so at the lower level you've got
fine grain temporal scales so fast time
scales and that would be for me
analogous to the anterior insula Network
that has been shown to be very much
related to the perception of faster time
scales at around
125 milliseconds so it's very present
oriented so that is one level of
granularity the default mode network is
much more a granular so it's much more
thinking about longer term Trends and
for mental gravity so when there's when
you've got centrality you've got
nestedness of those time scales they're
sort of able to harmonize with one
another even through you know neural um
oscillations like you've got that's G
norof northop's work which is looking at
spao temporal alignment of those time
scales so that's when you're feeling
good and you're feeling not overly
centralized I think that's when the
power of the dmn becomes too
overweighted a healthy or you know a
light state of being is when there is
alignment between spao temporal
scales so yeah it's the difference it's
the connection so if there's a dimension
of the self from anterior insula and I
should do it this way anterior insula to
default mode then the nestedness of
those scales is very
important wow very interesting on like a
little bit less of a neurobiological
note that makes me think about
estimating time estimating like double
click speed all the way on through
seconds and minutes and hours and days
and you know there's decades to take
weeks and weeks to take decades all that
kind of discussion and a day on Earth is
like this long in this other thought and
then those kinds of uh compression and
dilation are
used to point towards the direction of a
distribution it's kind of like saying
yeah from this GPS coordinate to there
you go this many East and that many
North and then similarly in cognitive or
narrative spaces like oh I was looking
for this kind of album but a little bit
more of that and from like this period
or with
faster beats yeah exactly so that kind
of like rate and gravity
connection it's also so
concordant yeah it's it's very clear and
there's Paul Badcock's work so the
hierarchically mechanistic mind with who
did work with Carl so he's also done
work on um the social adaption theory of
depression so there's mapping there
between his thoughts about the nesting
of sort of evolutionary time scales
through to you know
ontogeny um and then fast neural time
scales um and the disturbance of that in
depression so the social and emotional
disturbance of that alignment in
depression that
you depression is a way
of sort of calling out to other people
that you need help so Barbie is saying I
need other people I'm not just happy in
myself I'm calling out to others I need
support to get myself vertical again and
yeah there's a nice Synergy there with
Paul's work as
well yeah that's awesome I was thinking
of a few other like you mentioned a
person collapsing at the end of a
sporting event and how that's a
combination of like muscular fatigue and
the desire to have the homeostatic set
point B down because they want to be
resting closer to sleep all these
different things or the symbolic meaning
of it and and all that and then I
thought about the float tank experience
and um fun fun house rides uh amusement
park rides like spinning and uh and the
dipping and then weightlifting as kind
of an integral Through Time potentially
reducing the perceived weight load yeah
I mean so how would you just say at this
at these early days for the um the
Gravity Research program like how do you
take a phenomena and just sort of as
you've probably done many times like try
to work through it in this gravitational
way I think multi multidisciplinary
approaches is the only way to go so got
the guy in America doing gut brain stuff
so gut um gravity there's also Mark
Whitman who I uh published a paper with
on Consciousness on time Consciousness
he's very much into flotation tanks and
using that to alleviate anxiety and
depression I also think that
psychedelics there's something about
going on a trip there's the
phenomenology of you know
expansive space and time that happens
within um Asos cyber trip that we can
talk about that is the therapeutic angle
is something about SpaceTime curvature
or um the reentering of self an altered
state of self altered state of
consciousness so I think there are
multiple ways to look at
it so you know different interventions
different conditions and different sort
of emotional states that we're trying to
um trying to model without you know
forcing people into doing weightlifting
and saying it's all about this one
monolithic way of doing it like Anna was
saying like it's not just about sacred
spaces that are tend to be expansive as
well so churches and larger spaces even
forests natural blue and green spaces
have that expanse to them that's sort of
um therapeutic in a way I think there
are multiple multiple ways of looking at
it it's like I suppose it's like
predictive processing that's a way of
looking at things that you can apply to
different fields I think mental gravity
is something like that it's very
foundational it's kind of um Central and
implicit in many fields of work so I'm
hoping to work with Mark on
flotation with um Brennan in America on
the gut brain stuff with Anna about and
Nick on you know cooh homeostasis and
the development of graviception In Utero
I think there are many many ways to look
at
it awesome yeah
Anna thank you so much l this is really
really interesting um I have a question
related to the to the fact that um so um
I understand that verticality is super
important but
um don't you think that is also that
connected verticality is connected with
the fact with The Locomotion with the
fact that people can when they are
vertical they can basically just like
you know go there in the world and find
food you know self and make sure sure
that and that's that's it's not
necessarily because it's not enough just
to stand right no yeah vertical it's
like if you're still still standing
vertically is not going to get you very
far the same way if you stay still like
laying down it's it's all the same right
um so um how you see this like
verticality in relation to being static
and being um active so I think the
active component is like related to
motivational control so explore and
exploit behaviors so being able to
explore if you're vertical you have
greater degrees of freedom of movement
than when you're lying down so it's
easier to get horizontal if you're
vertical but you also need a low center
of gravity need to maintain a a balanced
uh center of gravity in order to do that
so more agility more ability to move
side to side is about maintaining a low
center of gravity when you're vertical
so they're kind of working in
combination so I spoke to Nick Wilkinson
about this and he's like okay it's when
you're born you're starting at this I
can't do anything I I can't move I can't
get myself up I'm dependent on my
Caregivers for all exploration of the
environment I can only see I can't
interact yet then over time as we
develop that motivation to explore comes
along with our ability to maintain
verticality and prevent fall so we start
by Falling a lot but that's because we
haven't leared that that low center of
gravity is what we need to regulate and
I think it's the same for mental gravity
you need to be vertical but maintain a
low center of gravity when you're
vertical that's most sustainable and
better for like exploring yourself
exploring ing you know your own
narrative if you're high and unstable
you may might be in a you know manic or
anxious or you know overly Upstate
that's not adaptive either so there's I
wouldn't want to say it's a u curve that
it's you know it's there there's an
Optimum state in between because it's
really complex but it's a bit like that
there's a a
combinatorial way of approaching gravity
that means it's not just about
verticality and it's not just about low
verticality or misalignment about
horizontal it's about a combination
dynamics of of the
two that that's an amazing point and I
think points to kind of a key
engineering trade-off which is the
bigger the building taller the building
more further out the building goes the
higher you can see and then the higher
the center of gravity becomes which then
under even small shaking of the land or
like Tower of Pisa status that becomes
comes unstable so then when skyscrapers
are built there's a heavy weight to move
the center of gravity down and to dampen
all these kinds of things that allows
like taller narrative construction so
that's super interesting and then I
thought about insects and not just
flying insects because there the
verticality is not associated with sleep
like an ant nestmate will be active at a
given elevation and then stop and rest
but they're not going down whereas
mammals even ones that are on quadruped
um Locomotion they still do go down when
they're cowering or like curling
up but in the insects they they can't go
well you know outside of the ones that
like do and all the stuff like that but
just in general a ground walking insect
doesn't go down so that really isolates
out the affordances and kind of
possibilities for movement because I
think Anna made a great point that
humans the verticality becomes also
associated with like being able to move
basically so being down it's like you're
caught on flat feet it's not even just
being standing you have to be like in a
little bit more of a poised posture to
react to basically anything even to
catch something very light like thrown
at you so that's very interesting how
the philogenetic priors which go far
deeper than any of
our um at least symbolically describable
or understood cultural priors which also
are very relevant and recent but these
kind of batera or going on land or
having aquous components those are even
deeper and like you said they're
preverbal and then yeah for sure I yeah
yeah I think this version of mental
gravity is uniquely human I think I
don't know if we can generalize it I
think there might be different
homeostatic ways for those animals of
talking about it but I think this you
know our up down associations I think a
preverbal sort of you know non you know
they pan cultural but I don't think
they're inter species necessarily I
think it maybe for fish there's
something about neutral buoyancy as well
but for insects for the birds who knows
but that might be one of the
characteristics of their space your
temporal Consciousness who knows
yeah yeah like for a fish there's a
possibly strong environmental
correlation between like the density and
the temperature and the light and so
there's a affordance in principle to
move up but then they find themselves in
a niche that might be like seasonal but
still captures this kind of like density
light nutrient
envelope because that's
their
Niche yeah yeah oh yeah ecology it
really is like that and about finding
the right level of you know fly when
it's time to fly but then not fly when
it's not time to fly all that yeah so
you could you can do experiments with
that in you know fishing a tank that you
accelerate you know to different
g-forces and see how they behave
differently and what associations they
make with nutrition or not just buoyancy
but you know light like you're saying
there're probably prior from you know
evolutionary prize phenotypic um
philogenetic um prize in there that you
can elucidate yeah wow that's very
interesting and bacteria or other single
cell in even just small tubes there
could be gradient
centrifuge with with constructed
nutrient gradients that's awesome
experiment um on the active inference
side um you showed the particular
partition with the internal and external
and the sense and the action States the
four states so the three states the
sense internal and action are the ones
that are defining the agent or the or or
the organism and so I was thinking like
what is a heavy sensory experience well
heavy metal a heavy cake something that
and then what's a heavy action possibly
it doesn't need to be even any more
literal than um heavy deadlift or it
could be a very burdensome task that's
hard to to push and then heavy internal
States so it almost has a heavy and
light not veilance
axis but just in this kind of mul
dimensional space of active inference
agents and models there is kind of a
separate heavy and light for these three
different parts of the particular thing
so I think that also just speaks to the
um
applicability it's not saying that those
three states of the thing are like the
same because they have to be welded
together by mental gravity it's actually
that gravity is like an analogy frame or
a metaphor that at the very least can be
used and is used normally and you could
also invent
speech things and just see which which
one sounds more normal which one sounds
more like the language model wrote it
and just used never seen
before gravitational language versus
anti-gravitational language just see
what the effect is maybe people prefer
one or the other if it's like
fantasy well there there's work been
done at my University at rmit in
Melbourne by someone who used Pro so the
upward and downward inflection of speech
so pitch
modulation to
analyze um speech of depressed and
non-depressed people as a kind of
biomarker so how people talk the
naturalness of their Pro is kind of
could be Diagnostic in a way because it
shows what sort of emotional veilance is
being used when they talk up and down
there's really a flatness of tone in
depression that people can sense and
people are expressing I think because of
this like you're saying what what's the
metaphor it's kind of like cognitive
load we think about depression as you
know the self has become too Salient
there's too much self-referential
information that's a drain on cognitive
capacity because it in itself is
cognitive load so their ability then to
think about the external world is
limited so I think there are again
multiple ways to look at this and
multiple ways to test it and intervene
and you know for therapeutic benefit so
yeah I think Pro as a what what's the
weight of Behavioral expression I think
there's posture there's facial
expression there's Pro
there's hes of wise looking at active
States as well so then to connect it to
writing first off it's very fascinating
that language models can through the
statistics of language without using
things like the pro and the timing just
from transcripts learn so much about
generating other realistic sounding
transcripts um so it's like what
information is in the procity and the
timing that's just very interesting but
it can be a
very I mean it helps us think about what
those kind of communicative techniques
are yeah and the symbolic basis of
language is more of a latecomer than the
kind of resonant nature of communication
on
these types of um on that level on that
vertical Dimension I suppose you'd call
it yeah yeah yeah and so Nick Wilkinson
who's worked with Anna talks you know
he's very interested in working on sort
of Soft Robotics so how do we
train uh an agent not based on
um you know a desired state that we
train forward but based on like that co-
homeostatic neutral buoyancy that's the
set point that's the attractor that
you're deviating from
and then all the implementations of that
regardless of physiology is translatable
then so that what you're trying to
approximate with standing you know
quadrupedally is neutral boyancy but
supported with different structures and
functions so I think there there's big
application there not just in terms of
language models but in terms of Robotics
as
well yeah all of the features of
embodiment in environments that we know
like if it was a muddy environment or if
it was a slippery one whatever the
embodiment
were saying you have to stay upright in
this environment and move is kind of
enough of a a forance to test and
explore the features of that landscape
if it has like gravel or what whatever
situation it has that's kind of what it
has to come back to otherwise like you
said to to to get up no more is to die
yeah exactly
yeah super um interesting Anna do you
have any last comments or
questions yes so I am I do
um uh so first of all I want to comment
very quickly when you just said uh L
because I think this is super important
so um there is right now we are in the
middle of like some sort of like like
shift in the perspective and I think
it's for the best in the sense like
instead of starting with something
highly sophisticated from the adult
Centric perspective we look at basically
how or going get there yeah and then we
see that
basically as I said well um the the body
needs to be like you know um embedded
into environment in a certain um states
that have been designed by billions of
years Evolution right so it's not it's
not propositional attitude content that
we can kind of like logically extract
from some abstract formula yeah um it's
it's something that is done through
trial and error and actually this is
something that changes all the time
because while you change environment you
need also to change posture and who know
it's like with all the pollution that we
have right now in the world maybe we're
going to adapt and develop new organs of
s yeah uh so so this that's um I think
that's that's something very important
but
um I I I really like the paper and I
really like the the way you you know um
bring the like
the um the basis back in this in the
core right like uh in in under the
spotlight but my question is to you um
so uh that that's that's very beautiful
way to um understand like
psycho pathology in terms of like uh you
know heaviness and I was actually
thinking that light and light means both
light in sense like not heavy but light
like in sense like you know dark not
dark
right so that's that's also beautiful
but um so how you include basically the
social component in it so the role of
the other in terms of like this Dynamic
of the gravity because we um um
interestingly enough people who are are
depressed or something they disengage
also from social interaction so it's
like some sort of like
flatness uh not uh and heaviness but um
not just heaviness but also like
disengagement from the active
exploration of environment be it
physical like you know going to the gym
or social like going to meet friends
yeah so what is the role of the other in
your model for this like um up and down
um uh a structure so I think that I
would go back to Paul Badcock's work
about the social risk hypothesis of
depression that it's a bit like okay you
take MDMA to have an extreme High
knowing that two days later you're going
to have an extreme
low I think his argument if I have it
correctly is that depression is kind of
similar that it's it's actually a call
out to other people to say I'm going to
be horizontal I'm laid out I don't have
any energy I need you you to help me
bootstrap and get back to being vertical
but that can become pathological not by
any sort of neural Dynamics it's not a
brain disorder in that sense it's a
social disorder because that care is not
forthcoming or it's not um it's not
appropriate or it's not effective so I
mean we look at a lot of the social
determinants of mental ill health that's
the field that I work in really dayto
day is
how do we promote and promote mental
well-being and prevent mental health
conditions by uh mod modifying risk and
protective factors so that risk that I
suppose the depressed person is taking
is they're saying I'm the only hope that
I have left I have none for myself is
that someone else will come and bring me
back into connection with the world I
can't do it I've run out of energy it's
like a the idea that um depression is
failed anxiety there's an anxious phase
prior to depression of reaching for
connections reaching for stability and
then when that has failed then it's like
I I have nothing left so I think it it's
a way of depathologizing the individual
destigmatizing individual and looking to
their environment to say how is society
how are other people letting this person
down how have they been let down by the
world around them so I think it
naturally implicates others and take
even though the individual is focused on
the self the effort from you know a
therapeutic angle needs to be from the
external whether it's the natural you
know uh green and blue spaces can be
therapeutic to connect to the natural
world or connect to the social
world yeah that's that's super important
thank you and not necessarily sometimes
we let people down but in most of the
case also we put people down you know
like put me down H yeah and let me
down the the the other can be for the
better and for the worst
right yeah also on the gravity and the
multi player multi-agent strange
attractors so there's like the three
body problem binary stars all these
asteroid belts all these different
stable configurations or unstable
configurations or chaotic or rhythmic
all those different movements and then
on the perspectival part there's the
world at the center self at the center
ego Centric view which is our kind of
undeniable object related visual system
and then there's the kind
of other
centrism like the sun everyone on the
earth will reference the Sun as the
centor point or there's kind of in
principle like a omnic
centrism but that's always alluded to as
like kind of in
principle true but then it doesn't ever
license any kind of perspectival
analysis except hypocritically because a
sensor has to be
chosen even if it's like a purely
homogeneous gas then the center of
gravity is just the center of the
space and so it's like there's so much
there with um how diffused the material
is and then well the gas clouds that are
really far away they have centers of
gravity so just because the Mist is very
ephemeral at the time scale that we're
moving doesn't mean that for like a
redwood tree or for something like a
bacterium it doesn't have a totally
different materials property so we can't
really say like how the niche is
by itself it's not like the desert is
just hot because it still might be too
cold for some
other adjacently living creature yeah
exactly so there are me there are
gravity models of Economics as well so
it's not just like we're talking we're
extending the physics of gravity for the
first time into mental the mental domain
they've been using gravity models it's
Newtonian gravity it's how sort of
cities or states trade with each other
where you're analogizing Mass to the
size of the population and then the
transfer of force is the transfer of
goods or services or people or whatever
so I think there's a way to apply this
at different scales as well to say okay
if Society is coherent and nested and
you know based on sort of topographical
or topological features of that Society
you can start to say well where are
people going to fall down in this area
here is where you're going to see an
increase in anxiety and depression which
is what we're seeing now we're seeing
okay we're using metaphors like Society
is fracturing or you know there's this
over centralization of power in you know
the top you know the 1% of the
population so the people at the bottom
are struggling so I think there are ways
to also take this the mental gravity
idea and apply it at different social or
societal scales as well
awesome yeah well Anna if you have any
last comments or questions and then
otherwise you can have the last word on
like where we go or what do we do but
Anna first then llin no I don't I don't
have any last words so I'm going to let
back last thanks for joining Anna thank
you so I think um to sum up I think okay
mental gravity this is one um aspect of
sort of bio
gravitation that we can look at I think
the conversations that I'm having with
people sort of around the world in
different uh domains in different fields
there is a way to
make I know kind of a discipline out of
this or at least a network of people who
are interested in the effects of gravity
on whatever it is whether it's the gut
whether it's the brain whether it's
development whether it's
Psychopathology Consciousness whatever
so my call out is to people if you're
interested and if you want to make
contact I am thinking of trying to sort
of become a node in that Network and try
and um bring people together people like
Nick Anna is interested given his work
he's going into robotics or he's
interested in going into robotics so I
think there are many different fields
that can come together to say okay we're
all talking about the same thing how can
we sort of formalize it get some you
know agreement and some principles and
all be working from you know at least a
point of point of connection action and
discussion so that's hopefully where I'd
like to see this go not just in
theoretical you know advancement but in
socially I think we can bring some of
these ideas
together and Daniel thank you for having
me thank you for contacting this has
been great it's forced me to really get
my ideas in order and be able to
communicate them so thank you for the
opportunity and to the active inference
Institute thank you thank you up up up
yep up up up all right thank you see you
all next time thank you
bye